Guide to the Isaac Leroy Shaver Papers, 1893-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Isaac Leroy Shaver papers 1893-1982
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Shaver, Isaac Leroy, b. 1893
13.0 linear feet Extent: 4000 Items
Isaacy Leroy Shaver (1893-1984) was a Methodist clergyman and missionary to Japan from the 1920s to the 1960s. The collection includes sermons, correspondence, photographs, printed material and published works related to Shaver's missionary work in Japan and Idaho. The material ranges in date from 1893-1982.
shaveril
Language: Material in English and Japanese
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Isaac Leroy Shaver Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1983-1986.
Biographical Note
Isaac Leroy Shaver was born in Rowan County, North Carolina in August 1893. He graduated from preparatory school at Rutherford College in 1915 and from Trinity College (now Duke University) in 1919. That same year, he married Pearl Tesh and soon thereafter, moved to Japan to begin work as a Methodist missionary. In 1924, he returned to Durham where he graduated with a master's degree from Duke University in 1925. Over the next several years, Shaver and his family moved between Japan and the United States, spending almost a year in Korea as well. During World War II, Shaver served as a Methodist minister to a Japanese community in Caldwell, Idaho and worked on behalf of Japanese held in U.S. detention centers. After the war, Shaver returned to Japan to continue his missionary work until returning to Idaho in 1959. He retired from his work as a pastor in 1969 and moved back to North Carolina with his wife. Shaver died in 1984.
Collection Overview
The collection consists of sermons, personal files, photographs, diaries, and appointment books. The sermons are largely from the 1940s-1960s. The sermon notes are in English, though some were transliterated into Japanese. The personal files include correspondence, church bulletins, baptism and marriage records from Idaho, family papers, passports, and clippings. Some correspondence, largely from 1942, concerns Shaver's work on behalf of Japanese held in U.S. detention centers. The photographs include eight albums and numerous loose pictures which have been placed in archival sleeves. The majority of the images are in black and white and were taken in Japan. Some were take at various locations in the United States. Photographic subjects include children, families, congregations, conference attendees, landscape/exterior views and the Shaver family. The printed matter/published works include books written about Japan and Christianity, the mission field, and sermons. There are also several Bibles, hymnals (some in Japanese), prayer calendars, and appointment books. The material that has been sent to the Preservation Dept. within Perkins Library includes photographs and certificates of achievement. The collection ranges in date from 1893-1982.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Shaver, Isaac Leroy, b. 1893; Missionaries -- Japan -- Correspondence; World War, 1939-1945 -- Japan; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States -- Japanese Americans; Japanese Americans -- Evacuation and relocation -- 1942-1945; Sermons, American -- Translations into Japanese; Evangelicalism -- Japan; Photographs -- Japan; Japan -- History -- 1926-1945; Sermons
Related Material
Park-Lambuth-Sherertz family papers, 1825-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke University
Mary McMillan Papers, 1936-1997 and undated (bulk 1952-1991)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library at Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Sermons, circa 1930s-1960s, (2 boxes)
  This series contains a sampling of Shaver's sermon notes, largely from the 1930s-1960s. The majority of the sermons notes are in English, although there are some that were transliterated into Japanese. Each folder contains multiple sermons, typically with a sermon index at the beginning of each folder. Sermon titles include On Holding Fast, Search the Scriptures, Three Crosses on Calvary, Dare to be Different, and Christmas Then and Now.
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Notebook, 1956-1957; Sermons, 1919-1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Funeral sermon notes, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Personal Files, 1890s-1980s, (1 box)
  This series includes correspondence (some of which pertains to Japanese held in U.S. detention centers during World War II), church bulletins, clippings, baptism and marriage records from Idaho, papers regarding the Anti-Alien Bill in Arizona, and family papers.
  - Correspondence, 1893-1925 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1936 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1941 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, 1942 Jan.-June (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, 1942 July-Dec. (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence, 1944-1948 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951, 1953, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1964, 1968-1971, 1974-1977, 1982, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Anti-Alien Bill in Arizona, 1933, 1935-1936 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    Includes clippings and correspondence
  - Caldwell, Idaho Church Bulletins, circa 1941-1947 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Kuna Methodist Church (Caldwell, Idaho) Bulletins, 1961-1962, 1965, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Miscellaneous Church Bulletins, circa 1935-1970s (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Caldwell (Idaho) Japanese Methodist Church, circa 1942, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    Includes lists of members
  - Kuna (Idaho) Methodist Church Membership, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Kuna (Idaho) Methodist Church Baptism Records, 1942, 1946-1947, 1961-1968 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Kuna (Idaho) Methodist Church Baptism Records, 1954-1968 (1954-1960 incomplete) (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Marriage Records, Caldwell and Kuna, Idaho, circa 1941-1969 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Papers: China, Korea, Japan, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Journal of the Pacific Japanese Provisional Annual Conference, 1943, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 79)
  - Clippings (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - Trinity College/Duke University materials, circa 1893-1935, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Rutherford College materials, 1912-1916 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Pearl Shaver materials, 1916, circa 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - Shaver Family: Miscellaneous materials, circa 1913-1955 (Box 3, Folder 84)
    Includes passports and other travel documents
  - Isaac Leroy Shaver biographical materials (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Preacher Licenses, 1911-1913, 1917-1918 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Miscellaneous Newsletters, 1936, 1942, 1945, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1913-1970s (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1913-1970s (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder 89)
- Photographs, circa 1920s-1970s, (2 boxes)
  This series includes photograph albums and loose photographs (largely black and white) that document Shaver's time in Japan and to a lesser extent, Caldwell, Idaho. The majority are unidentified and undated, although the bulk appears to have been taken post-World War II, likely during the 1950s. Many of the shots are posed although there are a good number of candid shots throughout the collection. In addition to serving as a missionary to Japan, Shaver also worked briefly in Korea. Some of the images from the late 1930s could possibly be from there. There are also family photographs.
  - Photograph album, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 90)
    Includes: images of conferences; church congregations; Greencastle, Indiana; Oita, Japan; the Shaver family; outdoor shots of Japan; Japanese orphans; Caldwell, Idaho; Camp Chickamauga; the 187th American Airborne Regimental Combat Team; photographs from the dedication of the American Airborne Memorial Children's Home (Eiko-en, 1952)
  - Photograph album, circa 1950s (Box 4, Folder 91)
    Includes: images of dedication of the American Airborne Memorial Children's Home (Eiko-en), Japanese orphans, the Shaver family, Japanese children at play, Camp Chickamauga.
  - Photograph album, 1920s-1930s (Box 4, Folder 92)
    Includes: group shots of congregations and possibly conference attendees, outdoor shots of Japan, the Shaver family, Japanese and/or Korean children and families.
  - Photograph album, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 93)
    Front and back covers are separated from the album. Includes: outdoor shots of Japan, groups shots, congregations, Japanese children, Japanese women, Japanese families, the Shaver family, weddings.
  - Loose album pages, 1920s-1930s (Box 4, Folder 94)
    Images of the Shaver family, outdoor scenes of Japan and Korea, groups, and congregations.
  - Loose album pages, 1940s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 95)
    Images of groups, conference attendees, weddings, Japanese families, and the Shaver family.
  - Loose album pages, 1930s-1950s (Box 4, Folder 96)
    Images of groups and landscapes in Japan and Korea
  - 35mm negatives, 1940s-1960s (Box 4, Folder 97)
  - Photograph album, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 98)
    Images of Japanese and/or Koreans at work, groups, congregations, the Shaver family, images of destroyed buildings, outdoor shots of Japan and/or Korea.
  - Postcard album (Japan), undated (Box 5, Folder 99)
    Colored postcards from Japan
  - Photograph album, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 100)
    Images of groups, congregations, the Shaver family, Japanese children.
  - Photograph album, 1940s-1950s (Box 5, Folder 101)
    Images of Oita, Japan, kindergarteners and their mothers, kindergarten teachers, the Shaver family, teachers' wedding, field day.
  - Loose photographs: Oita Church, portrait and wedding photos (Box 5, Folder 102)
  - Loose photographs: Dr. J.C. Rowe, circa 1880s-1890s (Box 5, Folder 103)
    J.C. Rowe was the father of Trinity College professor Gilbert Rowe
  - Loose photographs, circa 1920s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 104)
  - Loose photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 105)
  - Loose photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 106)
  - Loose photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 107)
  - Loose photographs and postcards, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 108)
  - Loose photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 109)
  - Loose photographs, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 110)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 111)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 112)
  - Loose photographs, 1940s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 113)
    Includes photographs of Hiroshima, circa late 1940s
  - Loose photographs, 1940s-1970s (Box 5, Folder 114)
  - Loose photographs, 1919-1960s (Box 5, Folder 115)
  - Loose photographs, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 116)
    Mostly from Caldwell, Idaho
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 117)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 118)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 119)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 120)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 121)
  - Loose photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 5, Folder 122)
- Diaries and Appointment Books, 1939-1975, (1 box)
  This series includes small diaries, appointment books, prayer calendars, and address books kept by Shaver and his wife, Pearl Shaver.
  - Diary and prayer calendar, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 123)
  - Diary and prayer calendar, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Diary, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Diary, 1942 (Box 6, Folder 126)
  - Diary, 1943 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Diary, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 128)
  - Diary, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 129)
  - Diary, 1946 (Box 6, Folder 130)
  - Diary, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 131)
  - Diary and account book, 1948 (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - Diaries, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - Diary, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Diary, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 135)
  - Diary, 1952 (Box 6, Folder 136)
  - Diary, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 137)
  - Diary, 1954 (Box 6, Folder 138)
  - Diary, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 139)
  - Diary, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 140)
  - Diary, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 141)
  - Diary, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 142)
  - Diary, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 143)
  - Diary, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 144)
  - Diary, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 145)
  - Diary, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 146)
  - Diary, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 147)
  - Diary, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 148)
  - Diary, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 149)
  - Diary, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 150)
  - Diary, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 151)
  - Diary, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 152)
  - Diary, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 153)
  - Diaries, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 154)
  - Diary, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 155)
  - Diary,1972 (Box 6, Folder 156)
  - Diary, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 157)
  - Diary, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 158)
  - Diary, 1975 (Box 6, Folder 159)
  - Mrs. Shaver's Diary, [1955?] (Box 6, Folder 160)
  - Address book, undated (Box 6, Folder 161)
  - Diary, [1949?] (Box 6, Folder 162)
  - Account book, undated (Box 6, Folder 163)
  - Book of names, undated (Box 6, Folder 164)
  - Account book, undated (Box 6, Folder 165)
- Printed Matter/Published Works, (4 boxes)
  This series includes books written about Japan and Christainity, missions, sermons, as well as Bibles and hymnals. Handwritten notes can be found in most of the printed matter/published works. Some of the hymnals are in Japanese.
  - Bibles, hymnals, and prayer calendars (Box 6a)
  - Books related to sermons, ministers' manuals (Box 7)
  - Books related specifically to Japan and/or Christianity (Box 8)
  - New Testament, books related to missions, Christianity (Box 9)
- Oversize Items, (9 items)
  - Oversize photographs and papers (Opaperfolder 1)
    Includes: Panoramic image of California Street Community Church and its Japanese/Japanese-American congregants; panoramic image of an unidentified group of conference attendees, taken in Seattle, undated; Pan-Am certificate "Domain of Phoebus Apollo," given to Shaver after he crossed the International Dateline, dated 1954 Feb. 20; five documents written in Japanese; certificate naming Shaver an Elder of the Methodist Church, 1922 Aug. 29